All right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. So today's דף Daf is ק"א
Kof-Aleph and we had because we had introduced the issue about why
ערב פסח Erev Pesach is different, why does the משנה Mishna single
out ערב פסח Erev Pesach that you stop eating from מנחה Mincha
onwards and it introduced the whole issue that in general on ערב
שבת Erev Shabbos you stop eating onwards, said, well, even those that
debate it, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi would agree ערב פסח Erev Pesach
you know, by ערב פסח Erev Pesach that's special, introduced us to
the whole question that eating on ערב שבת Erev Shabbos stopping when
it arrived to be שבת, Shabbos, being פורס מפה, Pores Mappa, spreading
out a cover on the bread on the meal in general case
by שבת Shabbos if you had already had the food out, certainly
if you were already eating and wanted and now it became night,
you would be spread a cover over the food and then make
קידוש Kiddush and now we're into the whole discussion no longer about
פסח Pesach but about שבת Shabbos and קידוש Kiddush and המוציא Hamotzi
particularly now with the focus on קידוש. Kiddush. So let's pick up
from where a little we'll backtrack a little bit about just to
get us back into the flow of it from the very bottom
of ק"א עמוד ב'. Kof Aleph Amud Bais. אותם בני אדם, Otam
Bnei Adam, two lines from the bottom of ק"א עמוד ב', Kof
Aleph Amud Bais, אותם בני אדם שקידשו בבית הכנסת, Otam Bnei Adam
Shekiddshu Bebeis Haknesses, those people that make קידוש Kiddush in the שול.
Shul. So you heard קידוש Kiddush in the שול, Shul, so what's
the story? So are you יוצא? Yotzei? So אמר רב Amar Rav
ידי יין לא יצאו, Yedei Yayin Lo Yatzu, it doesn't count for
יין, Yayin, ידי קידוש יצאו, Yedei Kiddush Yatzu, it counts for קידוש.
Kiddush. So we know what it means it counts for קידוש. Kiddush.
What does it mean it doesn't count for יין? Yayin? So it's
going to seem pretty clearly from the continuing discussion and this is
the way the רשב"ם Rashbam has to explain it, which is this
is not a שבת Shabbos question, this is a ברכות Brachos question.
If you made בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen in the שול,
Shul, yes you were יוצא קידוש, Yotzei Kiddush, but now you go
home, that's an interruption, you left the שול, Shul, you went home,
if you want to continue to drink wine you have to make
another בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Pri Hagafen. That's a principle called שינוי
מקום. Shinuy Makom. When you change location, even presumably if you had
it in mind, the very fact that you're in a different location
requires a new ברכה. Bracha. So that's what רב Rav says. So
fine, that's the ברכות Brachos issue, that's not directly our concern, but
we will get back to that. The focus is ידי קידוש יצאו,
Yedei Kiddush Yatzu, that it counts for קידוש Kiddush even though there
was no meal there. ושמואל אמר, Ushmuel Amar, שמואל Shmuel says אף
ידי קידוש לא יצאו, Af Yedei Kiddush Lo Yatzu, you didn't fulfill
קידוש Kiddush as we'll see the principle of שמואל Shmuel holds the
principle that we take for granted, אין קידוש אלא במקום סעודה. Ain
Kiddush Ela Bimkom Seuda. אלא לרב, Ela LeRav, says the גמרא Gemara
according to רב, Rav, למה לי לקידושי בבי כנישתא? Lama Li Lekiddushei
Bebei Knishta? Thank you so much. If you're יוצא קידוש Yotzei Kiddush
in שול, Shul, why bother making קידוש Kiddush again at home? Okay,
we know according to שמואל Shmuel why you make קידוש Kiddush again
at home, because you weren't יוצא. Yotzei. But according to רב, Rav,
why make קידוש Kiddush again at home? כדי להוציא בניו ובני ביתו,
Kedei Lehotzi Banav Ubnei Beiso, because you're not the only person in
the universe. You were יוצא Yotzei in שול, Shul, but there's a
lot of people at home that weren't יוצא. Yotzei. Your wife, your
kids, anybody else, guests. So for them you go ahead and you
make קידוש Kiddush again, which is fine because the principle is אף
על פי שיצא מוציא, Af Al Pi Sheyotzei Motzi, even though you
were יוצא, Yotzei, you could be מוציא Motzi other people. But the
קידוש Kiddush works for anybody who hears it and wants to be
יוצא Yotzei with that and doesn't want to go ahead and make
it again at home, then you could be יוצא Yotzei with the
קידוש Kiddush in שול. Shul. That's what רב Rav says. ושמואל, Ushmuel,
so according to שמואל Shmuel that you weren't יוצא, Yotzei, why do
we do the whole thing at all in שול? Shul? למה לי
לקידושי בבי כנישתא, Lama Li Lekiddushei Bebei Knishta, why did you make
קידוש Kiddush in the שול Shul at the בית כנסת? Beis Haknesses?
לאפוקי אורחים ידי חובתן, Leafokei Orchim Yedei Chovatan, yes
you're not יוצא, Yotzei, but the guests, they are יוצא. Yotzei. Why
are they יוצא? Yotzei? דאכלו ושתו וגנו בבי כנישתא, Deachlu Vshatu Vgano
Bebei Knishta, they eat, drink, and sleep in the שול. Shul. So
again, as I mentioned yesterday, תוספות Tosafot says it doesn't literally mean
in the sanctuary, you're not allowed to eat and drink and sleep
there, but in some side room. Okay, but that's the location where
they'll be eating. And drinking and sleeping seems to be thrown in
for, you know, just for the heck of it. But that's fundamentally
where they'll be eating. So therefore it is a קידוש במקום סעודה
Kiddush Bimkom Seuda and that the גמרא Gemara introduces is the principle.
דאזל שמואל לטעמיה Deazal Shmuel Letamei and שמואל Shmuel goes according to
his reasoning, דאמר שמואל Deamar Shmuel says אין קידוש אלא במקום סעודה,
Ain Kiddush Ela Bimkom Seuda, קידוש Kiddush is only, can only take
place in the place where you are eating. I want to repeat
some of the important points I said about this yesterday. Number one,
the fact that according to שמואל Shmuel they're יוצא Yotzei but you're
not means that although some people have it as a מקום סעודה,
Mekom Seuda, if you are listening and it's not a מקום סעודה
Mekom Seuda for you, you're not יוצא. Yotzei. It doesn't matter that
for other people it's a מקום סעודה. Mekom Seuda. That is very
important again because what you'll find, I find frequently, is a lot
of people aren't מקפיד Makpid at, particularly at a קידוש Kiddush of
a שול, Shul, to make sure they have מזונות. Mezonot. They figure
the rabbi made קידוש, Kiddush, he had
מזונות, Mezonot, and I don't have to have מזונות, Mezonot, right? It
was a good קידוש, Kiddush, so I can go ahead and eat.
No, it only counts for you if it's a מקום סעודה Mekom
Seuda for you. So if you want to be יוצא Yotzei with
a קידוש Kiddush you're hearing in שול Shul or anywhere you go
to somebody's house, whatever the case might be, you have to make
sure that you have a סעודה, Seuda, you have מזונות. Mezonot. For
now I'll say מזונות, Mezonot, we'll discuss what סעודה Seuda means in
a minute. That's principle number one. Point number two is that תוספות
Tosafot says it sounds like the guy who's making קידוש Kiddush is
not necessarily one of the guests. He's just, you know, somebody a
regular person in the שול, Shul, he's a שליח ציבור, Shliach Tzibur,
whoever he is. So it sounds like, you know, you could argue
otherwise, but it sounds like that for him it's not a מקום
סעודה Mekom Seuda and nevertheless it counts for the guests. Why? So
presumably it's a... That it's a מקום סעודה makom seudah for them,
not for him to be יוצא, yotzei, that we just said a
minute ago doesn't work, but in order for it to be a
good קידוש kiddush for them, he can make it even though it
doesn't work for him, he can make it so that it can
work for them. Which again is a little funny because you know
why is that a ברכה לבטלה? bracha l'vatala? It's not working for
him. But as I pointed out in a way it's not that
different from even after I was יוצא, yotzei, I can make for
you. Right? So if I can make, I made בורא פרי הגפן
borei pri hagafen מקדש השבת, mekadesh hashabbat, I made Friday night and
then you show up, your guest who came late, you ask you
would like me to make קידוש kiddush again for you, you don't
want to make your own קידוש, kiddush, I'm allowed to say the
whole thing again, even though with this second one I'm not being
יוצא. yotzei. So here too you have something somewhat parallel with the
first one I'm not being יוצא yotzei because it's not a מקום
סעודה makom seudah for me. But since it works for you, I'm
able to say it and it's not a problem of making a
קידוש, kiddush, a ברכה לבטלה. bracha l'vatala. Now what about nowadays we
say it when people aren't going to be eating in שול? shul?
So how's how why are we saying it? And תוספות Tosafot actually
says in that scenario you shouldn't, ברכה לבטלה. bracha l'vatala. But our
practice is that we do say it and as I pointed out
again yesterday, we have other phenomenon like this that start in order
to be assist people that need this help essentially, but once it's
established it becomes part of the liturgy and we do it regardless.
So the biggest example is חזרת הש"ץ, chazarat hashatz, that we repeat
the שמונה עשרה. shmoneh esreh. The original תקנה takkana was for people
that didn't know the דאוונען davening themselves, you don't have סידורים, siddurim,
people aren't literate anyway, but it was at the time when it
was all oral, you didn't have סידורים, siddurim, very little was printed.
How are you supposed to remember the whole שמונה עשרה? shmoneh esreh?
Particularly, I mean this is why particularly it comes up around ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah because you have a huge שמונה עשרה shmoneh esreh
on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and you only say it twice a
year. So anyway, and therefore the שליח ציבור shliach tzibur says it.
So should we not be saying it if people, everybody knows the
שמונה עשרה, shmoneh esreh, nobody needs him to repeat? And there were
those that said that. But we actually have established it, it has,
it became part of the liturgy and we say it now and
it's not considered a ברכה לבטלה, bracha l'vatala, it's just essentially considered
the נוסח nusach that we do in שול, shul, that this is
part of what we do. רב סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik by the חזרת
הש"ץ chazarat hashatz went even further to make it a whole separate
status of what it means to דאווען. daven. You're not just דאוונינג
davening as an individual in the midst of the ציבור, tzibur, which
is what you do when you're doing your private שמונה עשרה, shmoneh
esreh, but you're דאוונינג davening as an as a corporate entity of
a community, which is what you do when you repeat it, so
it gained new significance. But that's after, but that wasn't its origin.
Okay, and here too it would be the same thing. Another example
about this would be
lighting חנוכה Hanukkah candles in the שול. shul. Nobody's being יוצא, yotzei,
but you make a ברכה. bracha. Okay, but originally that was not
the function of it. Originally תוספות Tosafot is right. From the simple
rule of the גמרא, Gemara, if nobody is being יוצא yotzei we
shouldn't be doing it in שול. shul.
You did it once, didn't you eliminate חזרת הש"ץ? chazarat hashatz? What
are you going to do about קדושה? Kedusha? Let's just say, alright,
and we don't we don't need קדושה, Kedusha, the only way you
can do that is through חזרת הש"ץ.
chazarat hashatz. All right, I'm not getting into this, not our discussion.
But the other question is, so
according to
those who say to repeat it when you get home or even
when you get home to מוציא motzi your בני בית, bnei bayit,
so is there any preference to who would do it? In other
words, is it better to get the guests to do it?
Right, so that was a question asked yesterday whether we say that
there's a preference to do it or not.
I'm going to
I'm going to bracket that, that's more of a ברכות Berachot discussion,
but it is a discussion. For example, there's a lot of interesting
issues like when we say, you know, שומע כעונה, shomea k'oneh, is
it better to you know, I get up and I make קידוש,
kiddush, I say does anybody like to make קידוש kiddush themselves? So
no no no, you make, you make. Somebody says yeah, I want
to make myself. So why? So maybe they just like making קידוש.
kiddush. But maybe they feel like why should I be יוצא yotzei
שומע כעונה? shomea k'oneh? Why should I just be like I said
it? Maybe I should actually say it? Okay, is there a preference
to say it or to be יוצא yotzei or is it okay
to be יוצא yotzei with somebody else? Some say maybe it's a
preference to be יוצא yotzei with somebody else because ברוב עם, b'rov
am, then you do it as a community not as every individual
ברכה bracha at all. So similar type of an issue can be
asked. Yes, in general we do say that even though if you
are already יוצא, yotzei, better to have somebody who wasn't יוצא yotzei
to say it. That we do say. But again some of those
preferences are not so black and white. One other point I I
just wanted to mention about what תוספות Tosafot infers from this גמרא
Gemara is he says it also sounds like you don't have to
drink the wine. Right? Because because it sounds like you know, he
says he says the language there should sound like
take a look at the first תוספות Tosafot on ק"א ע"ב, kuf
amud bet, ידי קידוש יצאו yedei kiddush yatza'u אף על פי שלא
שתו af al pi shelo shatu רק שיטעום המברך rak sheyitaom hamivarech
או אפילו אחד מהם o afilu echad meihem כדאיתא בסוף פסחים k'deita
b'sof Pesachim ולכתחילה צריך שיטעמו כולם. u'l'chat'chila tzarich sheyitaamu kulam.
It's not black and white, but it doesn't sound like they're passing
the cup around. It sounds like one person is making קידוש. kiddush.
Okay, you could say not that way. Anybody who wanted to be
יוצא yotzei had to make a point of drinking it. But that
is another discussion and that I think many of us know, right?
A lot of people know you're not you know, I'm not מקפיד
makpid to drink the wine, I'm יוצא. yotzei. So it's interesting, you
can hear קידוש, kiddush, hear קידוש kiddush and be יוצא yotzei without
drinking the wine from a person who himself is not יוצא yotzei
because he's not staying around for the סעודה, seudah, but the one
thing you do have to do after you heard קידוש kiddush is
eat the is eat the meal. It's a little ironic to be
יוצא קידוש, yotzei Kiddush you have to eat the meal not drink
the wine. What is this an issue
of this קידוש במקום סעודה Kiddush bimkom seudah that you're not יוצא
yotzei the wine, to go back to? Is it really an issue
of במקום סעודה bimkom seudah or an issue of the wine? Okay,
yes. What is this an issue of this שינוי מקום shinuy makom
that's not just to the wine, to go back to? Is it
really an issue of במקום סעודה bimkom seudah or an issue of
the wine itself? For example, don't we sometimes when we're doing lunch,
I notice people will make קידוש kiddush, and eat like the first
bit of חלה Challah in the סוכה Sukkah and then move upstairs?
But they're eating the same wine.
Okay, so we're going to talk about that. All right, so that's
coming later today. That's coming later today.
I'll pass that, but can you eat an orange? Right. Someone else
says a ברכה bracha for?
Yes, so that's a good point. So if I want to be
מוציא motzi you as a ברכת הנהנין, birchat hanenin, I can, but
then I have to actually be נהנה. neheneh. I have to derive
a הנאה hana'ah because that's הנאה, hana'ah, הנאה hana'ah is pleasure. If
I want to make a ברכה bracha before food for you, I
actually have to eat as well because that's not a sense of
a מצוה ברכה mitzvah bracha that we're sort of communally obligated and
you're obligated and I'm obligated and I'm obligated also to help make
sure that you're יוצא yotze and therefore even if I've already made
it, I can make it again. Here it's really about the personal
pleasure I'm about to derive and therefore I have to- now if-
if I'm making it for myself, you can listen and be יוצא.
yotze But I have to start by making it for myself, it's
really rooted in the idea of the personal pleasure. Now the issue
comes about the בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen by the קידוש,
Kiddush right? Because let's say I've already made בורא פרי הגפן Borei
Pri HaGafen for myself, but that's a- so to what degree? So
there's a discussion about that in the גמרא Gemara where it basically
says that no, that because that's part of the קידוש, Kiddush, then
it can be incorporated into the קידוש Kiddush, and becomes like the
מצוה ברכה mitzvah bracha of the קידוש. Kiddush But normally, if I
want to be מוציא motzi you with a ברכה bracha I made,
let's say המוציא, HaMotzi, right? Which is all about the ברכת הנהנין
birchat hanenin there about the normal ברכה bracha to derive pleasure, I
can't make it for you if I've already made it for myself,
unless I have to make it again for myself. Okay, so let's
keep on going now.
What's going on there? All right. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. So אין
קידוש אלא במקום סעודה. ein Kiddush ela bimkom seudah.
Now why אין קידוש אלא במקום סעודה? ein Kiddush ela bimkom seudah?
I'll repeat what I said before. There are two reasons given. The
רשב"ם Rashbam gives either the reason that because קידוש Kiddush. is said
on wine, for wine to have some significance and weight, you know,
it's wine during a meal, that's not- that's not like a random
glass of wine, it's like, you know, the wine, you know, it
gives it some significance, some anchoring. And the other explanation is he
quotes a פסוק pasuk of וקראת לשבת עונג. vekarata l'Shabbat oneg. במקום
שאתה קורא לשבת, bimkom she’ata korei l'Shabbat, where you declare Shabbat, that's
where you should have the enjoyment of Shabbat, which seems like that
it is in order that the עונג שבת oneg Shabbat or the
meal be introduced by the קידוש, Kiddush be framed by the קידוש.
Kiddush, And that raises, and we saw that before, about you make
קידוש Kiddush. and then you bring out the meal, you make קידוש
Kiddush and then you uncover the bread. And that raises the question
that if you don't have קידוש במקום סעודה, Kiddush bimkom seudah, what
was the problem? Was the problem that the קידוש Kiddush wasn't a
good קידוש Kiddush because it didn't have the right type of wine
essentially, or is the problem that the meal was lacking as a
סעודת שבת seudat Shabbat because it was not introduced by a קידוש?
Kiddush So keep that in mind as we discuss in a minute
what constitutes מקום סעודה. makom seudah. So let's read a little bit
further now in the גמרא. Gemara. Says the following. סבר מינה. Savar
mina. So this is קידוש Kiddush? that שמואל Shmuel says אין קידוש
אלא במקום סעודה. ein Kiddush ela bimkom seudah. סבר מינה, Savar mina,
we thought to say, הני מילי מבית לבית. hani milei mibayis lebayis.
What's considered to be the same place? When is it- I mean
let me rephrase that. When is it a problem of a different
place? When you go from one house to another house. אבל ממקום
למקום, aval mimakom lemakom, but if you go from one location to
another, בחד ביתא, bechad beisa, in one house, לא, lo, that would
not be a problem. Now all right, all right, all right, let's
read a little. So we thought that two places in one location
would not be a problem. Now אמר ליה רב ענן בר תחליפא.
amar lei Rav Anan bar Tachlifa. רב ענן בר תחליפא Rav Anan
bar Tachlifa says זימנין סגיאין, zimnin sagi’in, many times, הוי קאימנא קמיה
דשמואל, havei kamina kamei d'Shmuel, I was in the presence of שמואל.
Shmuel. Right, שמואל's Shmuel the one who says אין קידוש אלא במקום
סעודה. ein Kiddush ela bimkom seudah. Many times I was in the
presence of שמואל. Shmuel. דנחית מאיגרא לארעא, denachis me'igra le'ara,
and he went down from the rooftop to the ground, והדר מקדש.
vahadar mekadesh. Meaning he was, you know, they were all sitting around
up the rooftop
and he made a point of going from the roof to the
ground and then he made קידוש. Kiddush Meaning he could have made
קידוש Kiddush. up on the roof, but he didn't make קידוש Kiddush
up on the roof, he made a point of going down to
where we're going to be having our main meal and making the
קידוש Kiddush at- and making it a קידוש Kiddush on the ground
floor of where we're going to be having our main meal. Now
why did he do that? Presumably he was afraid that had he
made קידוש Kiddush up on the roof and then they moved to
the ground, that would be considered a new מקום makom and it
wouldn't have been considered
במקום סעודה, bimkom seudah, literally in the same place. Now what's interesting
is that this is considered to be, right? So- hold on one
minute-
so you see that even from one place to another place in
the same house is considered to be a problem of not being
במקום סעודה. bimkom seudah. סעודה seudah and therefore he had to be
sure and make sure he was going to be at the right
place. Now even though that's true, תוספות Tosfos makes a qualification for
that שיטה. shitah. And תוספות Tosfos says that would only be a
problem
if wait a minute let me just check one thing.
Right, תוספות Tosfos says that would only be a
problem. Okay, so תוספות Tosfos
says two things. So now the גמרא Gemara has established that you
can't have it in two places in the same house. So first
let's look at this small תוספות Tosfos of ממקום למקום בחד ביתא.
mimakom lemakom bechad beisa. So תוספות Tosfos says and that we decided
is a problem because he had to make sure to go from
the roof to the floor that that would be considered two locations.
So he says פירש מחדר לבית או מבית לעלייה peirush micheder levayis
o mivayis lealiyah from one like room in the house to another
or from the ground floor to the upper floor כמו מאיגרא לארעא
kemo maigra leara like this case of going from the roof to
the ground. אבל מפינה לפינה יש קידוש aval mipina lepina yesh Kiddush
but if it's from one corner of a room to another corner,
that would count. כי היכי דלא חשיב שינוי מקום בסמוך ki heichi
delo chashiv shinui makom besamuch so we'll see that later on. So
number one is two different locations in the same large room like
you have a huge social hall and you're making קידוש Kiddush at
one end of it and the other end, that's considered still במקום
סעודה. bimakom seudah. Okay, now how big of a difference is considered
to be a you know when is it considered to be a
different a different מקום makom and when is it considered to be
מפינה לפינה? mipina lepina? You know let's say you go ahead I
mean you know what we do like you make קידוש Kiddush up
here sometimes and then what do they do when they have a
קידוש Kiddush in שול? shul? They make קידוש Kiddush up here and
then everybody goes down and eats. Okay so how do we do
that? That could certainly seem to be like you know מאיגרא לארעא
maigra leara right it's one level to a different level. Right? So
if you take a look at תוספות Tosfos ידי קידוש יצאו yedei
Kiddush yatzeu go back to that תוספות Tosfos on קמ"ב. kuf mem
bais. תוספות Tosfos says like this. He says wait
one minute. Okay
והמקדש vehamikadesh it starts with a line פסק במגילת סתרים pasak beMegillat
Setarim about six lines down on the תוספות. Tosfos.
פסק במגילת סתרים. pasak beMegillat Setarim. I forget what that...
מגילת סתרים Megillat Setarim is a well it means something else in
the גמרא Gemara but it's a work of רבינו ניסים גאון. Rabbeinu
Nissim Gaon. I don't know why it's called מגילת סתרים Megillat Setarim
but it's a work of רבינו ניסים גאון. Rabbeinu Nissim Gaon. So
it says פסק במגילת סתרים והמקדש שדעתו לאכול במקום אחר יכול להוציא
את האוכלים שם pasak beMegillat Setarim vehamikadesh shedaato leechol bemakom acher yachol
lehotzi es haochlim sham that if you have your intention when you're
making קידוש Kiddush to eat in another place, that works.
I'm sorry no no wait wait I'm sorry I jumped ahead.
I'm sorry that wasn't the one I wanted.
No that was the case of where the guests are eating. I'm
sorry that was the case I said before where you're not eating,
the guests are eating. One minute. No hold on hold on.
Okay ומיהו ממקום umihu mimakom I'm sorry it's about twelve lines down
it starts with the word כגון. kegon. Do you see it? Three,
four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten, yes about fifteen lines down.
That's the one I want. ומיהו ממקום למקום בבית אחד umihu mimakom
lemakom beveiyis echad what we just said was no good, two different
locations in one house כמו מאיגרא לארעא. kemo maigra leara.
נראה דמודה שמואל nireh demodeh Shmuel it seems that שמואל Shmuel would
agree אם קידש באיגרא כדי לאכול בארעא דחשיב קידוש במקום סעודה. im
kiddesh beigra kedei leechol beara dechashiv Kiddush bimakom seudah. וכמוכח בירושלמי ukemochach
bYerushalmi
that if you have intention to go from one place to another
in the same house, that can work. Okay now that's not so
clear in the גמרא Gemara because if that were true why do
you have to go from the roof to the floor? Just say
I'm like we say we're making קידוש Kiddush now and we're going
to finish eating down there. Okay but תוספות Tosfos wants to incorporate
this ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. There's really no evidence to this in the גמרא.
Gemara. If anything the simple sense of the גמרא Gemara is not
this way. But תוספות Tosfos actually says and this actually is the
הלכה halacha that there are two degrees of a different מקום. makom.
There's literally another house okay which is like you're making in שול
shul you want to be יוצא yotze. at home. There it's clear
from שמואל Shmuel there's no way that's going to work. Like the
only reason we're making קידוש Kiddush in the שול shul is for
people that are eating here. If you're going home there's no way
my קידוש Kiddush in the שול shul can help you even if
I have in mind that I'm going to make קידוש Kiddush here
and go ahead and finish eating at home. Okay but when we're
talking about two locations in the same
building מאיגרא לארעא maigra leara there if you have it in your
mind it can work. And that's why in all these שולס shuls
they'll make upstairs in the שול shul and then they'll go to
the social hall for the קידוש. Kiddush Okay? So the simple sense
of the גמרא Gemara is there's no way a קידוש Kiddush. in
one location in a house building can work for another location, one
room for another room. Okay? But then but then the גמרא Gemara
it raised it and it shot it down. But then תוספות Tosfos
comes based on the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and this becomes the הלכה halacha
that if it's in the same building it will work as long
as you have it in mind.
Yeah you said you need some מזונות Mezonot there or?
Downstairs you need מזונות. Mezonot. No that's the whole point. The whole
point is that it counts as במקום סעודה bimakom seudah if you
had it in mind and if it's in the same building.
So you need some some people you know I I tried to
do this but you know they make קידוש Kiddush downstairs where they
release you know some stuff. Is it better to do that like
to is there a preference?
Yeah well you could argue that there's a preference you know because
but... terms of the, I mean a preference because, you know, it's
possible to argue in the גמרא Gemara otherwise, but in terms of
the פסק psak accepted הלכה, Halacha, you know, this is taken as
a as a לכתחילה.
l'chatchila. Yeah. Does תוספות Tosafos consistently say yesterday where קידוש Kiddush is
introduced in סעודה Seudah and קידוש Kiddush is introducing סעודה? Seudah? Right,
so if you've popped off on
the balcony... Yeah, exactly. Right.
And that's the way you work.
That makes sense.
Right, exactly. That's part of the plan, so you see that as
preceding and connected to what comes next. Exactly. It's only when it's
a new idea then it's considered to be a new experience.
And the other and the other if your if your actions during
the week, if you're over this thing... Right.
And you regularly do this. Right. I'm not sure like you have
to be consciously, you know, voicing the words in your head הריני
מכוון Harei ani michaven etc., it's in the context you understand that
you're now going to continue, right? But I do think again the
simple sense psychologically makes sense. The simple sense of the גמרא Gemara
though is not that way, because then why would שמואל Shmuel bother
switching locations, right? He said he made a point of going downstairs
to make קידוש Kiddush once he made קידוש Kiddush upstairs.
Well, then he made it as a transition and then you have
to explain what is the point of the קידוש Kiddush transition?
Right, you mean that even having it in mind doesn't work.
It's the exact opposite. So why would there be this restriction? Your
explanation of yesterday made total sense in תוספות. Tosafos. If
not...
Yeah. Well, because it would require, it's the same idea of introducing,
but just more in a visible way than in what's going on
in your head, you know, to see it as introducing you need
them physically juxtaposed. All right, yes, do you want to say something?
No? All right, let's continue. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says,
where were we? Okay. אמר ליה רב עננא בר תחליפא, Amar lei
Rav Anan bar Tachlifa, זימנין חדא, zimnin chada, oh we already did
that. אבל רב הונא סבר אין קידוש אלא במקום סעודה, Aval Rav
Huna savar ein Kiddush ela bemakom seudah, רב הונא Rav Huna holds
קידוש Kiddush must be in the place of the meal. רב הונא
קדיש ואיטפרא ליה שרגא. Rav Huna kadish ve'itfara lei shraga. רב הונא
Rav Huna made קידוש, Kiddush now here's, obviously something went different than
what he intended. He made קידוש, Kiddush, he's planning on eating, and
then the candle blew out.
ועיילו ליה מאני לבי גנני דרבה בריה, Ve'ayilu lei manei levei gananei
deRabbah bereih, and so he brought his vessels, like you know, his
plates, his eating vessels to the בית גנני, bei gananei, which basically
means like the choson's חופה chuppah to the wedding house of רבה
Rabbah his son, and רבה Rabbah recently had just got married like
a few days ago. Okay, and he knocked on the door and
said, hey son I'm moving in, okay,
at least for שבת. Shabbat. דהוי שרגא, Dahavei shraga, that there there
was a lamp.
וקדש וטעים, Vekadesh veta'im, and he made קידוש Kiddush, and he ate
there, but he wasn't going to go ahead, he obviously wanted, he
didn't want to eat where it was dark, and he felt he
had to make קידוש Kiddush again since now he's eating here. אלמא
קסבר אין קידוש אלא במקום סעודה. Almah kasavar ein Kiddush ela bemakom
seudah. You see that קידוש Kiddush has to be in a place
of סעודה, seudah, he had to make קידוש Kiddush again. Now, I
want to say, well you know I'll read one more line and
then I'll go back to it. ואף רבה סבר אין קידוש אלא
במקום סעודה, Ve'af Rabbah savar ein Kiddush ela bemakom seudah, even רבה
Rabbah holds this.
דאמר אביי, De'amar Abaye, אביי Abaye said, כי הוינא בי מר, Ki
havina bei mar, when I was at the house of Master, which
is רבה, Rabbah, his master, his Rebbe. כי הוה מקדש, Ki havah
mekadesh, when he made קידוש Kiddush on Friday night, and we were
the students and we were learning there because his house, you know,
could also mean like his ישיבה, yeshiva, we were there. אמר לן,
Amar lan, he would say to us, טעימו מידי, te'imu midi, have
a little bite to eat right now before you all
go home because דילמא אדאזליתו לאושפיזא, dilma ad'azlitu le'ushpiza, because maybe by
the time it takes you to go to your your inn, your
home, so maybe they weren't living at home, but okay, they were
going to have קידוש Kiddush over there with רבה Rabbah and then
they were going to go to wherever they were staying.
איטפרא לכו שרגא, Itfara lechu shraga, the candles at your host's house
will have blown out, or at the inns you're staying at will
have blown out. ולא מקדש לכו בבית אכילה, Vela mekadesh lechu beveit
achilah, and therefore you haven't made קידוש, Kiddush you won't make קידוש
Kiddush, there because
you don't want to, you know, who wants to eat where it's
dark? So you're not going to make קידוש Kiddush there because it's
going to be completely dark. ובקידושא דהכא לא נפקיתו, Uvekiddusha dehacha lo
nafkitu, and you won't be יוצא yotzei with the קידוש Kiddush you
just heard from me. דאין קידוש אלא במקום סעודה, De'ein Kiddush ela
bemakom seudah, because קידוש Kiddush is only where you have a meal.
So you see he said basically, look, I'm making קידוש, Kiddush that's
all very nice for me, but if you want to be יוצא
yotzei you better have a bit to eat. And here again we
see even though I'm being יוצא, yotzei if you want to be
יוצא yotzei, you have to have a bit to eat because, well
we're going to get to what a bit means, because if wherever
you're going and that's where you're planning on having your main meal
and something might happen and you won't have an opportunity to make
קידוש Kiddush, there and therefore, you know, the candle blow out and
won't be wine, assuming the candle blow out so then you won't
even eat there. But anyway you are not going to be יוצא.
yotzei If you need to be יוצא yotzei. with this קידוש Kiddush
you're not going to be יוצא yotzei unless you have something to
eat. Now I want to make a few points about this. Number
one is what's clear is is that it says אין קידוש אלא
במקום סעודה, ein Kiddush ela bemakom seudah, you have to make קידוש
Kiddush again. Okay, now does that prove that the point of קידוש
במקום סעודה Kiddush Makom Seudah is to give is to give significance
to the קידוש? Kiddush Not necessarily because even if the problem of
קידוש במקום סעודה Kiddush Makom Seudah was to define the
שבת Shabbat meal by being... So the fact that I have to
make it again doesn't show whether the problem was that it wasn't
a good קידוש Kiddush? or whether it shows that the problem was
was that I'm going to have my סעודות שבת seudos Shabbos that's
not going to be introduced by קידוש. Kiddush Either way, I need
to make קידוש Kiddush. again. But it's clear that if it's not
במקום סעודה, bimkom seuda, you have to make it again. Now, how
much do you have to eat? Both of these stories both had
the phrase תעימו מידי. teimu midi. Have a- have a bit to
taste, have a bit to eat. So if you take a look
at תוספות, Tosafos,
right, and תוספות Tosafos says תעימו מידי, teimu midi, נראה nireh תוספות
Tosafos says, right before the lines at the bottom, דהיינו תעימת לחם.
dehaynu teimat lechem. It means bread. So even though it says a
little bit, it means a little bit of bread, okay, even though
it says taste. Then in פרק קמא דשבועות perek kamma deShavuos כי
אמר אינשי ניטול מידי ואזיל ואכלי ושתו. ki amri inshi nitol midi
va'azil ve'achli veshasu.
The גמרא Gemara has exactly this phrase in שבועות. Shavuos. People say
let's have a bit to eat, and what they mean is a
little bit of bread, a little bit of wine. It means a
little meal, but it's still a meal. Okay. ומידי דמיא תרגימא להשלים
ג' סעודות שבת U'midi damya targima lehashlim gimel seudos Shabbos כמו בסוכה.
k'mo beSukkah. And if it's true that like let's say like delicacies,
meaning מזונות, mezonos, counts for ג' סעודות gimel seudos on שבת, Shabbos,
היינו דוקא בסעודה שלישית, haynu davka beseuda shlishis, אבל לא בסעודות ערבית
ושחרית שהם עיקר כבוד שבת. aval lo beseudos Arvis veShacharis sheheim ikkar
kavod Shabbos. Okay. That's only for סעודה שלישית, seuda shlishis, not שחרית
Shacharis and ערבית. Arvis. So תוספות Tosafos says we're talking about bread.
And what's תוספות's Tosafos proof or not necessarily his proof, but what
is implicit in תוספות Tosafos why it must be that we're talking
about bread? Because for your first two meals of שבת, Shabbos, you're
not יוצא סעודות שבת yotzei seudos Shabbos without bread, right? That's pretty
clear תוספות's Tosafos whole point. And therefore, קידוש במקום סעודה Kiddush bimkom
seuda has to mean bread. Which is clear therefore according to תוספות,
Tosafos, the idea of במקום סעודה bimkom seuda is what is defined
as סעודות שבת. seudos Shabbos. My first two meals, if they need
bread, if that's what I need for סעודות שבת, seudos Shabbos, then
that's where my קידוש Kiddush has to be, for my סעודות שבת.
seudos Shabbos. So that's what תוספות Tosafos says. The גאונים Geonim say
otherwise. The גאונים Geonim say that you could be יוצא קידוש במקום
סעודה yotzei Kiddush bimkom seuda with much less. There's even a position
in the גאונים Geonim that- and this almost makes the whole גמרא
Gemara absurd- is that במקום סעודה bimkom seuda is if you drink
a רביעית revis of wine. So if you had a significant amount
of wine, that's a במקום סעודה bimkom seuda because you're drinking wine.
You're not a little bit of wine, you have a full רביעית
revis of wine. So what's the whole discussion? Why didn't the גמרא
Gemara just say you know why we make it a joke if
you drink a רביעית revis of wine and you're יוצא? yotzei So
that's taking it to quite an extreme. But certainly להלכה, lehalacha,
the widespread פסק psak that's accepted is is that you're יוצא yotzei?
with a מזונות. mezonos. Okay, you have to have like a כזית
kezayis of a מזונות, mezonos, that counts for קידוש. Kiddush Now, this
debate seems to be exactly this question I introduced about what's the
importance of having the two of them together. If the importance is
that your סעודות שבת seudos Shabbos has to be introduced by קידוש,
Kiddush. תוספות Tosafos is right, it has to be bread, right? So
otherwise no good. But if the idea is to give some weight
to the קידוש, Kiddush, it's a significant one to the place where
you're just not סתם stam drinking a glass of wine but in
the context of something more significant, so fine, even other eating, even
a מזונות mezonos counts enough to give weight to קידוש. Kiddush, So
the fact that we rule that מזונות mezonos generally the assumption is
that we rule that מזונות mezonos counts seems to be that we
come down clearly on that side of the argument, that the purpose
of קידוש במקום סעודה Kiddush bimkom seuda is just to give weight
to the קידוש. Kiddush. You have מזונות mezonos and it's fine. However,
I don't know what your practice is, my practice certainly is, let's
say everybody's at shul, everybody had wine, had קידוש Kiddush. or whatever,
had some מזונות, mezonos, we all come home. Do you start שבת,
Shabbos, do you just start with המוציא Hamotzi or do you make
a בורא פרי הגפן? Borei Pri HaGafen? For a lot of us,
I think it feels weird. What? We're going to start with המוציא?
Hamotzi? So you do a בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen before.
It's not a ברכה לבטלה, bracha l'vatala, you want to have some
wine, you have some grape juice, you're allowed to make a בורא
פרי הגפן. Borei Pri HaGafen. But according to- well, the פסוקים pesukim
you say before on שבת Shabbos day don't mean anything. They're not
part of- the- the real קידוש Kiddush on שבת Shabbos day is
just בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Pri HaGafen. Okay. If I wanted to
get up and say ברוך אתה ה' בורא פרי הגפן, Baruch atah
Hashem Borei Pri HaGafen, that's it, that's קידוש Kiddush on שבת Shabbos
day. Okay. So anyway, what? I know, I know. So- so anyway,
so okay, maybe we're just doing because it feels right. But it's
possible to argue and this is, you know, this is sort of
the approach I take, is that not just that it feels right,
but actually it's a way of saying that may be both of
these positions, either my bread or maybe both are right. On the
one hand, I can be יוצא yotzei קידוש Kiddush in shul enough
to allow me to eat, because you can't eat without קידוש, Kiddush,
to say that having the מזונות mezonos gave weight to the קידוש
Kiddush and made it a valid קידוש. Kiddush. And therefore that was
okay, and therefore I was able to eat, you know, the whole
smorgasbord there because I had some מזונות. mezonos. But that doesn't satisfy
the idea that my סעודות שבת seudos Shabbos needs a קידוש Kiddush
to introduce it. So I'll make קידוש Kiddush again before my actual
meal. And that not just because it feels right but maybe because
there's this other
dimension. So it is possible that both are true, but I will
say that the simple
פסק psak in the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch and in the פוסקים
poskim is that you really only need מזונות mezonos and you technically
don't need it for the meal itself. Okay, but again I think
that a good argument could be made that you have both parts.
Yes, Dov.
You go to a big קידוש kiddush in שול shul שבת Shabbat
morning, you eat plenty of מזונות mezonos and other things, you make
קידוש kiddush beforehand. You get home, it's not סעודה שלישית. seudah shlishit.
Is it סעודה שלישית? seudah shlishit? So I was going to ask.
So can you have enough מזונות mezonos that it actually becomes your
real סעודת שבת seudas Shabbos without bread? There are times when you
have enough מזונות mezonos that it turns into קביעת סעודה kvias seudah
and that you actually will do ברכת המזון birkas hamazon afterwards and
so on. So that's possible. But you could actually fill yourself with
the smorg and you know and you're on your Atkins diet, so
you're only having, you're having all these great meats or whatever, but
you're only having a tiny bit of מזונות. mezonos. So then nobody
would say that that counts as סעודת שבת, seudas Shabbos, you know?
So, but you only have your little two loaves of bread.
There's a big discrepancy there because you
could have a whole meal. I understand. Yes, absolutely. According to the
גמרא, Gemara, there's no סעודה seudah without bread or maybe serious מזונות,
mezonos, and for us, we could imagine an entire meal that nobody's
having bread. Right.
Two questions. Does rice count as מזונות? mezonos?
So some say it, but generally for those, but generally the assumption
would be that real מזונות. mezonos.
And סעודה שלישית seudah shlishis is not introduced by קידוש, kiddush, so
that would not require מזונות? mezonos?
Right. Although no, no, but that does require סעודה. seudah. So what
constitutes סעודה seudah for סעודה שלישית? seudah shlishis? That's not a קידוש
kiddush question, that's a סעודה seudah question. But I did want to
say, and this is goes back also to this issue about about
introducing it. רמב"ם's Rambam's position is that סעודה שלישית seudah shlishis also
requires wine. רמב"ם's Rambam's position is
that all the סעודות seudos of שבת Shabbos should have wine with
them. So according to רמב"ם, Rambam, that idea that there's two things
being יוצא yotzei קידוש kiddush and having some type of a קידוש
kiddush introducing the meal, for the רמב"ם Rambam in a way you
have that because the same בורא פרי הגפן borei pri hagafen you
have at שחרית, Shacharis, you know, at the second meal, you have
at the third meal. For the רמב"ם, Rambam, you're supposed to have
wine with each of the meals. So you certainly see the idea
that there could be both of those aspects there. Last question. Yes.
I just wanted to make sure I understand. So you're saying for
the first two meals you have to have bread? So, right? In
other words, to be יוצא yotzei your? Yeah. So basically what we're
doing is, so we're not really being יוצא yotzei the שבת Shabbos
meal, but we are being יוצא yotzei קידוש במקום סעודה. kiddush bimkom
seudah.
Exactly. You're יוצא yotzei קידוש במקום סעודה, kiddush bimkom seudah, you're יוצא
yotzei קידוש, kiddush, and then you have your שבת Shabbos meal without
קידוש, kiddush, which I was saying is a little strange. So.
So that's why when we go home, we don't sing סעודה שלישית
seudah shlishis זמירות. zemiroos.
Right. Okay. Right. And we're מקפיד makpid to have it, the other
סעודה שלישית. seudah shlishis. All right. Fine. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay. איני, Aini, is this really true?
ואמר אביי, V'amar Abaye, כל מילי דמר, kol mili d'mar,
everything of the master, of רבה, Rabbah, הוי עביד כרב, hava avid
k'Rav, he would rule like רב, Rav, לבר מהני תלת דעביד כשמואל,
l'var mihani thlas d'avid k'Shmuel, there was only three times he would
rule like שמואל, Shmuel, רבה. Rabbah. What were the three times? מעבירין
מבגד לבגד. maavirin mibeged l'beged. שמואל Shmuel says you're allowed to take
ציצית tzitzis off of one garment to put it on another garment,
even though in the process you're removing the מצוה mitzvah from one,
it doesn't matter, you're going to transfer it to another, that's okay.
We're not going to get into what that debate is about. ומדליקין
מנר לנר, U'madlikin miner l'ner, very interesting, sort of
similar, parallel, you can although it's not exactly it's not really the
same, but whatever, structurally similar, you can on חנוכה Chanukah use one
חנוכה Chanukah lamp to light the other, and we're not concerned that
it seems like it's not respectful
to the נר חנוכה ner Chanukah that's already lit that you're using
it to light another נר חנוכה. ner Chanukah. Number two. That's also
שמואל Shmuel said, and רבה Rabbah ruled like that. והלכה כרבי שמעון
בגרירה. V'halachah k'Rabbi Shimon bigreirah. Good thing that we rule like that.
That's extremely important in all of הלכות שבת. hilchos Shabbos. Whether you
are allowed to, there's a debate between רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, if you're if you're dragging a chair across
a flowerbed, in your bed or backyard because you need to put
it somewhere else, and inadvertently you might come to make a חריץ.
charitz. So if it'll definitely happen, everybody says it's no good. But
if it's not necessarily it'll happen, are you allowed to drag the
chair knowing it might make a חריץ? charitz? That's considered the question
of דבר שאינו מתכוין, davar she'eino miskavein, something you're not intending which
will not definitely result. And we rule like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
and רבה Rabbah ruled like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, and like רב,
Rav, who oh excuse me like שמואל Shmuel who ruled like רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon against רב Rav that says it is allowed. Good
thing, because if not you just imagine what we wouldn't be able
to do on שבת. Shabbos. You can't walk on grass, you might
inadvertently pull out the grass, you can't and you couldn't do so
many things, you might inadvertently come to do something else. So, or
not come to but that action might might cause something else. Anyway,
so those three things he ruled like שמואל, Shmuel, but in all
other cases he ruled like רב, Rav, and here רב Rav is
the one that says קידוש kiddush you can make קידוש kiddush without
מקום סעודה. makom seudah. So how could it be that רבה Rabbah
is ruling like שמואל? Shmuel? So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
דתניא רבי שמעון אומר, D'tanya Rabbi Shimon omer, oh so it tells
you what the last one means. Interesting, it tells you the last
one, not the first two. גורר אדם מטה כסא וספסל בשבת, Gorer
adam mita kisei v'safsal b'Shabbos, a person can drag a bed, chair,
and bench on שבת. Shabbos. A bed or a chair or a
bench on שבת *Shabbat* across the field, ובלבד שלא יתכוין לעשות חריץ
*uvilvad shelo yitkaven laasot charitz*, as long as you're not trying to
make a furrow even though it might happen inadvertently. So how could
he here rule like רב *Rav* if רב *Rav* says you're allowed
to—how could he here excuse me rule like שמואל *Shmuel* that requires
it, doesn't he always go like רב *Rav*? So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says: כי חומרי דרב הוה עביד *kechumrei deRav hava avid*. No,
normally when רב *Rav* and שמואל *Shmuel* debate he always rules like
רב *Rav* when רב *Rav* is מחמיר machmir *machmir*, and there were
three times he ruled like שמואל *Shmuel*, שמואל *Shmuel* was more מקיל
*meikel*. But כקולי דרב לא הוה עביד *kekulei deRav lo hava avid*.
When רב *Rav* was מקיל *meikel* like in this case, he wouldn't
necessarily go like רב *Rav*. Here he'll go like שמואל *Shmuel*. שמואל
*Shmuel* says you need קידוש במקום סעודה Kiddush bimkom seuda *Kiddush bemakom
seudah*. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* is bothered because there's a גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
that says you're not supposed to
adopt always the חומרות *chumrot* of if there's a constant debate between
parties I'll always be מחמיר *machmir*. Okay, no, you either take one
position and you're consistent with it. So here it sounds like he
basically was going to go like רב *Rav* or שמואל *Shmuel* either
way לחומרא *lechumra*, okay, because I'll go like רב *Rav* when he's
the מחמיר *machmir* one. So תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says yeah but you
know you're allowed to do that if you're not being internally contradictory,
like if the different חומרות *chumrot* don't contradict one another. Anyway, that's
a separate conversation. Okay, but רבא *Rava* yes did here hold like
שמואל *Shmuel* against רב *Rav* and said אין קידוש Kiddush אלא במקום
סעודה bimkom seuda. *ein Kiddush ela bemakom seudah*. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. Now, that was the second part of their
debate. That was more interesting one which was about קידוש במקום סעודה
Kiddush bimkom seuda *Kiddush bemakom seudah* or more interesting I should say
for our issues of קידוש *Kiddush*. But remember there was the first
statement that they both agreed that it didn't count for בורא פרי
הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen, *borei peri hagafen*. Okay, if you moved even
if you were יוצא *yotzei* קידוש *Kiddush* you went home, you wanted
to drink wine, you had to make another בורא פרי הגפן borei
pri hagafen *borei peri hagafen*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now picks
up with that.
So it says like this: רבי יוחנן אמר אף ידי יין נמי
יצא *Rabbi Yochanan amar af yedei yayin nami yatza*. You know what?
If you made בורא פרי הגפן borei pri hagafen? *borei peri hagafen*
in שול *shul*, then it counts for the בורא פרי הגפן borei
pri hagafen *borei peri hagafen* for the wine you want to now
continue drinking at home. שמואל *Shmuel* says assuming that you drank a
little bit in שול *shul*, not just hearing the ברכה bracha, *beracha*,
but you drank a little bit, you heard בורא פרי הגפן borei
pri hagafen. *borei peri hagafen*, you can now go to another place
without making a new ברכה bracha *beracha*. ואזל רבי יוחנן לטעמיה *veazal
Rabbi Yochanan letaameih*. רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* goes according to his reasoning,
דאמר רבי יוחנן בר אבא אמר רב חנין בר אבא אמר רב
אסי אמר רבי יוחנן *deamar Rabbi Yochanan bar Abba amar Rav Chanin
bar Abba amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan*: אחד שינוי יין ואחד
שינוי מקום shinui makom אין צריך לברך *echad shinui yayin veechad shinui
makom ein tzarich levarech*. Whether you are changing the wine, you're opening
up a new barrel of
wine—whether you are—you made a בורא פרי הגפן *borei peri hagafen* and
now you're bringing out a whole new barrel of wine, white wine
instead of red wine, whatever it is—או בין שינוי מקום shinui makom.
*o bein shinui makom*—or whether you're switching locations, you do not have
to make another בורא פרי הגפן *borei peri hagafen*. Now, some people
might be aware of the הלכה halacha *halacha* that when you bring
out a new barrel of wine that you weren't intending, wasn't on
the table and it's a better barrel, you have to make הטוב
והמטיב *hatov vehametiv*. So you take a look, תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* points
it out, okay, תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot* says or the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*
points it out, we look at the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*: אחד שינוי
יין *echad shinui yayin*, שהביאו לו יין מחבית אחרת *sheheviu lo yayin
mechavit acheret*, ויש לו טעם משונה או גרוע או משובח *veyesh lo
taam meshuneh o garua o meshubach*, אין צריך לברך שנית על היין
*ein tzarich levarech sheinit al hayayin*. אבל הטוב והמטיב מיהו מברך אם
משובח מן הראשון *aval hatov vehametiv mihu mevarech im meshubach min harishon*.
Okay, and תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafot* says the same thing, first line תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafot*, שינוי יין אין צריך לברך *shinui yayin ein tzarich levarech*,
מיהו הטוב והמטיב צריך לברך *mihu hatov vehametiv tzarich levarech*, כדאמרינן בברכות
*kedamrinan biBerachot*. Okay, and then there's a question is it only if
the second wine is better, etc. whole discussion about הטוב והמטיב *hatov
vehametiv*. We're not talking about הטוב והמטיב *hatov vehametiv*. We're talking about
do you have to make another בורא פרי הגפן *borei peri hagafen*.
So רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says I don't care if you change
wines, I don't care if you change locations, you made a בורא
פרי הגפן *borei peri hagafen* you don't have to make another one.
And therefore if you heard קידוש *Kiddush* in שול *shul* and you
made בורא פרי הגפן *borei peri hagafen* and you drank a bit,
assuming you were יוצא *yotzei*, then you go home, you want to
continue drinking, you don't make another בורא פרי הגפן *borei peri hagafen*.
Unless you say
a ברכה אחרונה bracha achrona *beracha acharona*? Yeah, okay, that might take
it. מיתיבי Meitivi. *Meitivei*, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, I'll ask you
on this. And now we're going to focus on this question of
making another בורא פרי הגפן *borei peri hagafen*. שינוי מקום shinui makom.
צריך לברך שינוי יין אין צריך לברך *Shinui makom tzarich levarech shinui
yayin ein tzarich levarech*. So there's a ברייתא braisa, *braita* that's very
black and white: changing locations you have to make a new ברכה
bracha *beracha*, changing wines, barrels of wines, you don't have to make
a new ברכה bracha *beracha*. So you see you do have to
make a new one when you change locations. תיובתא דרבי יוחנן תיובתא
*Tyuvta deRabbi Yochanan tyuvta*. Okay, so much for that position. We have
a—that was a very quick discussion. Okay, but we're not done. So
now we've established new place has to make a new ברכה bracha
*beracha*, but just like we had the discussion by קידוש במקום סעודה
*Kiddush bemakom seudah* what's a new place and we said even from
the roof to the floor is a new place, here too by
שינוי יין *shinui yayin*—what's considered a new location, okay, that requires a
new ברכה bracha. *beracha*. חזי רב אידי בר אבין קמיה דרב חסדא
*Chazi Rav Idi bar Abin kameih deRav Chisda*. So רב אידי בר
אבין *Rav Idi bar Abin* was sitting in front of רב חסדא
Rav Chisda *Rav Chisda*. יתיב רב חסדא Rav Chisda *Yativ Rav Chisda*.
רב חסדא Rav Chisda, *Rav Chisda* was sitting, וקאמר משמיה דרב הונא
mishmei deRav Huna, *vekaamar mishmeih deRav Huna*. And saying in the name
of רב הונא Rav Huna *Rav Huna*: הא דאמרת שינוי מקום צריך
לברך ha de'amart shinui makom tzarich levareich, *ha deamrat shinui makom tzarich
levarech*. That that you said that changing locations needs a new ברכה
bracha? *beracha*, לא שנו אלא מבית לבית *lo shanu ela mibayit lebayit*.
That's only if again very similar language than before, if you're going
from one בית bayis *bayit* to another בית bayis. *bayit*. אבל ממקום
למקום mimakom lemakom. *aval mimakom lemakom*. From one location to another, presumably,
and now presumably as some have the גרסא girsa *girsa*, מפינה לפינה
pina lepina *mipina lepina*, okay, from one corner of a room to
another corner of a room. You have to realize that very often
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, like בית bayis *bayit*, when they refer
to another בית bayis *bayit*, it could have just meant another room
in the same building. So anyway, but we would assume that מפינה
לפינה *mipina lepina* לא *lo*, you would not have or ממקום למקום
mimakom lemakom. *mimakom lemakom* you don't have to make another ברכה bracha,
*beracha*. That's not a שינוי מקום shinui makom *shinui makom*. אמר ליה
רב אידי בר אבין הכי תני לה במתניתא דבי רב הונא Rav
Huna *Amar leih Rav Idi bar Abin hachi tani lah bematnita debei
Rav Huna*—ואמרי לה במתניתא דבי בר הונא *veamri lah bematnita debei bar
Huna*. We just like that we taught. In a ברייתא braisa? from
the school of רב חינך Rav Chinach or some say from the
school of the school of the son of חינך, Chinach, כוותך, kevaseich,
just like you, that if it's from one corner of a room
to another corner, you don't. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא רב
הונא מתני פסקא משמיה דנפשיה? Ella Rav Huna masni piska mishmeih denafsheih?
So what side, I don't get it? So if it's a ברייתא,
braisa, what's רב הונא Rav Huna, doing coming to teach us a
ברייתא? braisa He says, yeah, רב הונא מתניתא לא שמיע ליה. Rav
Huna masnisa lo shemia lei. רב הונא Rav Huna. didn't hear this
ברייתא, braisa. I mean who ever heard of a ברייתא braisa. from
דבי בר חינך? de-bei bar Chinach? What's that, you know? So he
never heard of that ברייתא. braita So he's telling us his own
opinion and lo and behold it turns out that it's confirmed by
a ברייתא. So now what do we know? That if שינוי מקום
shinui makom? requires a ברכה, bracha. not from one corner of a
room to another, but presumably from one building בית to another building
בית. And again, what בית to another בית here means is it
presumably means that it would include איגרא לארעא igra le-ara from one
room to another room as well in the same house presumably like
the discussion before of קידוש במקום סעודה would also be considered a
שינוי מקום. shinui makom. Now we have to ask what if you
had though בכוונה, bekavana, right, to be to
in order to switch rooms, what would that, would that change things?
But again, now we seem to be like we said that that
works by קידוש במקום סעודה if it's in the same building. Okay,
but presumably here different rooms, again, it's not explicit about different rooms,
different rooms usually gets categorized as בית לבית, bayis le-bayis, not פינה
לפינה. pinah lepinah. So therefore בית לבית, bayis le-bayis, so different rooms
presumably, although it's not black and white, would constitute שינוי מקום. shinnui
makom, But again, maybe having that in mind would be would be
acceptable. Yes?
איגרא לארעא Igra le-ara doesn't mean different rooms, it's different floors.
Different floors, right, maybe different floors are different than different rooms, that's
true.
Suppose you're in the dining room, you spread out to the den
in the living room on the same floor.
Right, that's the same thing?
Right, so maybe not. And maybe there's also a principle that if
one room is רואה, ro'eh, if it's visible from the other room,
and that's an important point, that it's certainly considered one מקום makom
if it's visible from one of the locations to the other. So
that's how do you define one מקום makom is through. And I
should point out, and this has to do with the גרסא girsa
of פינה לפינה pinah lepinah as opposed to ממקום למקום. mimakom lemakom
That the גמרא Gemara on the עמוד א amud aleph when it
talked about the roof to the floor described it as ממקום למקום.
makom lemakom, So and that was the roof to the floor. So
if you have the גרסא here ממקום למקום that it's okay, right,
so then that means that even that even the roof to the
floor would be okay. So exactly what's considered שינוי מקום shinnui makom,
is not clear. We have the two extremes: one building to another
building, yes; one corner of a room to another corner is not
a problem. And again, a room might be any place that you
can see, you know, any room that sees the other room, how
exactly that's defined. What about one room to another room, you know,
in the same building? Is that a שינוי מקום? shinnui makom, That's
not clear. We said that the הלכה halacha by קידוש is that
as long as you had in mind and it was in the
same building, that's okay. Here it's not clear which category that falls
into. Okay, let's see how the גמרא Gemara continues
now with this. Okay, ותו, vesu, in addition, יתיב רב חסדא וקאמר
משמיה דנפשיה, yasiv Rav Chisda veka'amar mishmeih denafsheih, רב חסדא Rav Chisda.
was sitting and saying in his own name, הא דאמרת שינוי מקום
shinnui makom, צריך לברך, that which we said that when you switch
rooms you have to make a new בורא פרי הגפן, לא אמרן
אלא בדברים שאין טעונין ברכה לאחריהן במקומן. lo amran ella bidvarim she'ein
te'unin bracha leachareihen bimkoman. That's only things that do not require a
final ברכה bracha. in that location. אבל דברים הטעונין ברכה לאחריהן במקומן
אין צריך לברך. Aval devarim hate'unin bracha leachareihen bimkoman ein tzarich levareich.
Things that require a final ברכה bracha. in that location
you don't have to. I'm going to read it and then I'll
explain it. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? לקביעא קמא הדר,
Lekvia kama hadar, you're going back to the original sort of established
meal, the original קביעות, kvi'us, you know where you sort of set
down your roots. What does this mean? It means here I am,
I'm drinking
my coffee and I'm going to go outside and continue drinking my
coffee. Okay, so I have to make another ברכה bracha when I
continue drinking my coffee when I go outside? Do I have to
go after I'm finished drinking my coffee, do I have to come
back here to this room and make a בורא נפשות Borei Nefashos
when I'm done with my coffee? The הלכה halacha. is no. That
things like שהכל, shehakol, I'll discuss what about the middle category in
a minute, but things let's say fruit and שהכל shehakol etc., those
types of things, you know, you go ahead and you make the
ברכה bracha, wherever, wherever you finish eating, it's not an idea of
going back. However, some people might be aware, you know, there's this
famous debate of בית הלל ובית שמאי Beis Hillel u-Beis Shammai that
you know you remembered after you left the place how far away,
you know, do you have to be, then you're still required to
go back and make the ברכה. bracha There's an idea of making
the ברכה אחרונה במקום סעודה, bracha achrona bimkom seuda, where is that?
That's most obviously about bread. When you have a meal like המוציא,
Hamotzi, that's considered to be you're setting down your roots, you're not
just eating it on the go, you're setting down your roots here.
This is your מקום סעודה. mkom seuda. So if you got up
and you left, then you have to come back and you have
to make the ברכת המזון Birchas HaMazon where you actually where you
started your meal, okay, במקום סעודה.
Now what falls into that category of מקום סעודה mkom seuda that
you have to go back to? The רשב"ם Rashbam says it includes
all שבעת המינים, shivas haminim, which includes wine and pomegranate and all
that type of stuff. תוספות says, and that gives him a lot
of heartache because this whole גמרא Gemara is talking about wine and
it would make every case one of those. So anyway, תוספות says
that's not correct. It's only about ברכת המזון, Birchas Hamazon, that's the
only thing. What about מזונות? mezonos? תוספות has a little bit of
a discussion about this. If you take a look at תוספות, he
says, אלא בדבר שטעונה ברכה, Ella bedavar sheteuna beracha, I'll try to
keep to the key line. He says,
לכן נראה, Lachen nireh, it's about ten lines before the lines get
wide, it starts with the line הלכה כמותו. Halacha kemoso. I don't
know if you see that. לכן נראה דיין וכל שאר המינים לא
הוי בכלל דברים הטעונים ברכה אחרונה במקומם, Lachen nireh deyayin vechol shear
haminim lo havai bichlal devarim hateunim beracha achrona bimkomam, אלא פת, ella
pas, but bread, וכל מיני פת שמברכין עליו המוציא, vechol minei pas
shemevarchin alav hamotzi, או שמא כל מיני מזונות שיש בהם מעין חמשה
הוי בכלל דברים הטעונים ברכה. o shema kol minei mezonos sheyesh bahem
meein hamisha havai bichlal devarim hateunim beracha. Maybe מזונות mezonos as well,
but definitely bread. Okay, so the idea is that you have to
go back, let's say certainly for bread and maybe מזונות, mezonos, and
that's basically the הלכה. halacha People completely reject the רשב"ם that applies
to שבעת המינים. shivas haminim. You have to go back and make
your ברכה אחרונה bracha achrona there. Now, why should that make a
difference for this question of whether you have to do a new
בורא פרי הגפן when you switch your location? Because if I am
having my meal here, and I'm having my bread meal and we're
really settling down our roots and we're being קובע koveia and we're
having bread, and we're drinking wine, okay, and then I'm going somewhere
else, right? So you might have said, how much more so going
somewhere else is like a, you know, different location. But the idea
is that it's all seen as sort of a connect- like rooted
in this original eating. Like this is where we're established. So even
if we're eating there, it's somehow like connected to the eating here.
Could be, you know, one way you could say this just is
just practically. I don't want to have to, if this is sort
of what the רשב"ם sounds like, if I didn't have in mind
when I was sitting here that the eating there should be a
continuation, then when I would go there, I'd have to before I'd
leave, I'd have to בענטש, bench, I'd have to wash, and make
a new המוציא hamotzi and all those things because, you know, because
the הלכה halacha, is you have to come back, you know, to
where you are. So clearly, since I wouldn't want to do all
that stuff, right, which would be required because when you move places
when you eat, clearly the eating that I'm going to continue to
do was always part of in my mind seen part of this
eating. That's sort of saying that that's what I would have chosen
out of an issue of convenience. But I don't think you have
to make it a psychological thing and an issue of convenience. I
think the idea is that if this defines my meal, then anything
I do, you know, like if I'm sort of, like if you
assume, like we're in a wedding, for example, and we're having the
main meal in a room and people are moving around in the
other rooms, you know, after they started the meal they're eating d'oeuvres
or whatnot, all of that is somehow an outshoot of where they're
really setting down their roots, where they're having their main meal, right?
Those things are considered an extension of that and not something new.
Whereas if I'm just סתם stam eating d'oeuvres, and I'm eating in
one room and then I'm in another room and then I'm eating
some more d'oeuvres, they're not connected, right? Everything is sort of very
ad hoc, it's just at the location it happens to
be. So then you need to make another ברכה? bracha Then you
need to make another ברכה, bracha because that what well if different
rooms in the same building is שינוי מקום. shinnui makom Okay, so
that's actually it's a little ironic because you would have thought the
more you're in one place a new place is different, but that's
the גמרא's phrase of לקביעותא קמא הדר. likvia kama hadar. You're going
back to where you originally made your established your meal. Okay, so
if you actually do you have to make a new בורא פרי
הגפן? Now, again, you know, do you have to make a new
בורא פרי הגפן when you switch places? So it says if all
you're doing is just סתם stam nashing, then yes, you're in a
new place it's a new eating. But if what you're doing is
you're having a real meal, and then you went somewhere else and
drink wine, that's all connected to that main meal that you're eating
elsewhere and therefore you don't
make another
בורא פרי הגפן.
I have a language question. Yeah. What do you mean יתיב רב
חסדא וקאמר משמיה דנפשיה? Yasiv Rav Chisda veka amar mishmei denafshei?
Because before we had רב חסדא Rav Chisda. said משמיה דרב הונא,
five lines from the top, right, יתיב רב חסדא וקאמרי משמיה דרב
הונא. Yasiv Rav Chisda vekamre mishmei deRav Huna. And now that was
the idea that ממקום למקום, you know, or מפינה לפינה is okay.
Now he's saying a new teaching but not in the name of
רב הונא, on his own authority.
Implicitly I would have thought he was still-
you might have said it's continuing his teachings in the name of
רב חסדא, Rav Chisda. exactly. words that he said in the name
of רב הונא. Okay. So that's a very important הלכה, exactly, comes
up all this time about like the, you know, going from one
room to another and you had it in mind, etc. So we
haven't even discussed whether having in mind helps or not. Let's take
a look at how the גמרא tries to prove this. So now
this is רב ששת אמר. Rav Sheshet amar. Now רב ששת Rav
Sheshet says אחד זה ואחד זה צריך לברך. echad zeh v'echad zeh
tzarich l'varech. I don't care whether you were in the middle of
a המוציא Hamotzi meal or whatnot. When you did a real שינוי
מקום, shinnui makom? again, maybe different rooms in the same house doesn't
count, but if you do a real שינוי מקום, shinnui makom. you
gotta make another ברכה. bracha, Now, by the way, we're only talking
about a new ברכה ראשונה. bracha rishona. We haven't discussed whether you
have to make a ברכה אחרונה bracha achrona in the same scenario.
תוספות,
it's not clear. תוספות goes back and forth about that. In the
scenario, you have to make a new ברכה ראשונה bracha rishona because
of שינוי מקום, shinnui makom does it also require to make a
ברכה bracha. אחרונה before you leave the place you're leaving?
Or is it just ברכה שאינה צריכה? bracha she'eina tzricha?
Or
according to רב ששת'ס Rav Sheshet's for his side, רב ששת Rav
Sheshet says you always make a new ברכה. bracha, Okay, so let's
take a look. מיתיבי. Meitivi, I have to by the way, I
should just mention, you know how in some of the restaurants they
have right by the washing station little pieces of bread? That's because
of the concern that שינוי מקום, shinnui makom although that's not the
same issue, but I mean it's not the same scenario, but that
the between the על נטילת ידים al netilat yadayim and the המוציא,
Hamotzi, a שינוי מקום shinnui makom, would be considered a הפסק hefsek
objectively. Even if, you know, even if you had in mind the
whole thing. So that's why they want there to be... Now that,
what degree is it a שינוי מקום? shinnui makom I mean, you
can see the place and it's all in... So again, there's also
very מחמיר ideas of what constitutes שינוי מקום. shinnui makom So this
שינוי מקום shinnui makom issue is something we tend not to be
sensitive about. We tend to assume as long as I'm still eating,
as long as I had it in mind, why does any of
this matter? But you see in the גמרא it's not פשוט. pashut.
Okay? So the גמרא didn't discuss the issue of having it in
mind yet, but anyway, the גמרא really seems the objective reality of
שינוי מקום shinnui makom could require a new ברכה. bracha. Yes. Okay.
Just like a הפסק, hefsek, that if you wash until you get
back to your seat.
Yes, but the הפסק hefsek might be the objective reality of שינוי
מקום, shinnuy makom not just the amount of time.
Or if you came in from the kitchen to the dining room.
Well, again, that's the case בית לבית, bayit l'bayit, פינה לפינה pina
l'pina and so on. Okay, so now the גמרא says like this.
מיתיבי, I'll ask you on this. בני חבורה שהיו מסובים לשתות, Bnei
chavura shehayu mesubin lishtot,
a group were says getting around and drinking, ועקרו רגליהם לצאת לקראת
חתן או לקראת כלה, v'akru ragleihem latzet likrat chatan o likrat kalla,
and they all got up to go, there was a wedding party
and they all took a little break, they heard there was better
food there or something. Anyway, no, they did it for the מצוה.
mitzvah. They heard there was a wedding party. כשהן יוצאין, Keshen yotzin,
when they're about to leave, אין טעונין ברכה למפרע, ein teunin bracha
l'mafrea, they don't have to make a ברכה מעין
שלש bracha me'ein shalosh or a ברכה bracha retroactively, meaning a ברכת
המזון. Birkat Hamazon.
כשהן חוזרין, Keshen chozrin, and when they come back, אין טעונין ברכה
לכתחילה, ein teunin bracha l'chatchila, they don't have to make המוציא. Hamotzi.
It's all a continuation, even though there's a שינוי מקום shinnuy makom
in the middle. Okay? במה דברים אמורים, Bamei devarim amurim, when is
this true? שהניחו שם זקן או חולה. shenihichu sham zaken o choleh.
If one guy, נבך, nebach, wasn't able to join them for the
party. So he created the sense of continuity. He was old, he
was sick, so they left him behind. אבל לא הניחו שם לא
זקן ולא חולה, Aval lo nihichu sham lo zaken v'lo choleh, if
they didn't leave anybody behind, כשהן יוצאין טעונין ברכה למפרע, keshen yotzin
teunin bracha l'mafrea, when they go out they better
בענטש bentch first. כשהן חוזרין טעונין ברכה לכתחילה, keshen chozrin teunin bracha
l'chatchila, they have to make a המוציא Hamotzi again. Now, I should
point out to you, this is a much bigger חידוש chiddush because
besides the fact that it says שינוי מקום shinnuy makom requires a
ברכה, bracha here it requires a ברכה even when you come back.
It's not just in the new place is it objectively a new
eating, but the fact that I went to a different place objectively
said I stopped, I interrupted what I did. And then even when
I come back, it's not considered a continuation.
Coming back is you're coming back to now it's a new meal.
It's a new meal. So it's a different idea. It's not just
שינוי מקום is a new experience of eating in a different place,
it's a new meal in a different place. But be- having experienced
a שינוי מקום interrupts the meal I was doing. One minute. So
מדקתני עקרו רגליהם, midekatani akru ragleihem, since it says they uprooted their
legs, which is a little bit superfluous, it means that there was
something that they were planted, that they had to uproot themselves, which
means it was a type of a קביעות, keviut, a fixed meal,
a meal that you would normally make a ברכה in the same
place like a
המוציא. Hamotzi. מכלל דבדברים הטעונין ברכה לאחריהם במקומן עסקינן, Michlal d'bidvarim hateunin
bracha l'achareihem bimkoman askinan, we're talking about a way in which they
were really like planted in that place, meaning that it was a
המוציא Hamotzi meal, something they would have to make a ברכה in
that location,
a ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon. So it's- a, that's the scenario, and
nevertheless, הטעמא, hataama, the only reason that they would not have to
repeat, you know, make a new ברכה, is שהניחו שם זקן או
חולה הוא. shenihichu sham zaken o choleh hu. That- that's only because
the- first that there was an el- somebody they left behind. כשהן
יוצאין אין טעונין ברכה למפרע כשהן חוזרין אין טעונין ברכה לכתחילה. Keshen
yotzin ein teunin bracha l'mafrea keshen chozrin ein teunin bracha l'chatchila. That's
because- that's when when they come back they don't have to do
a ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon or a המוציא. Hamotzi. אבל לא הניחו
שם זקן או חולה, Aval lo nihichu sham lo zaken v'lo choleh,
if they didn't leave anybody behind, okay, כשהן יוצאין טעונין ברכה למפרע
כשהן חוזרין טעונין ברכה לכתחילה. keshen yotzin teunin bracha l'mafrea keshen chozrin
teunin bracha l'chatchila. It's a little superfluous. Okay, but anyway, but it's
clear from that, that if they didn't leave anybody behind, they have
to make a ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon, they have to make המוציא
Hamotzi again. So why is this? Here would be a case where
it was a
המוציא Hamotzi meal and we see that the- if unless you had
somebody there to make a sense of continuity. the objective reality of
שינוי מקום requires a new ברכה. That's a proof against
רב חסדא. Rav Chisda Okay, but he's being מדייק medayek it more
than that because it says עקרו. akru. So it understands that this
was a case where they were having bread, and it's a proof
against
רב חסדא. שינוי מקום still requires a new ברכה, even when they
come back to the same place. קשיא לרב חסדא. kashya l'Rav Chisda.
That's a question to רב חסדא. So we'll just read the beginning
of the answer. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, amar Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak, said רב נחמן בר יצחק, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, מאן תנא
עקירה עקירות? man tana akira akirot? רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. No, no,
no, no. The author of this ברייתא that says עקרו רגליהם akru
ragleihem that you need to have an elder there, that's רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. But what we're going to see tomorrow, and well, and
here, is that the חכמים Chachamim argue on רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
and they say even if you didn't leave anybody behind, you don't
have to make another ברכה. Okay, so basically exactly this scenario: you
left, you came back, do you have to make another ברכה or
not? The debate of רב חסדא and רב ששת Rav Sheshet we're
going to see is a debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and
the חכמים Chachamim about whether שינוי מקום when you have a קביעות
סעודה keviut seuda requires a new ברכה or not. Okay, so from
tomorrow.